If Xie Jiayu knew you were going to harm her today,
谢嘉鱼若知道你今日要害她
I wonder what she would think.
也不知她会怎么想
Believe it or not,
不管你信不信
thank you for stopping me today.
今日多谢你拦我
I didn't want to do this.
我并不想这么做
Tonight is eventful.
今夜多事
You should return to the palace early, Your Highness.
县主还是早些回宫吧
Young Lord Xiao.
萧世子
Are you really confident
世子当真有信心
that you can protect them both in Jiankang?
能在这剑慷城之中护住他们二人
When winter comes and the grass withers,
待入冬草枯
the Northern Qin's forces will definitely come south again.
北秦虎狼定会再次南下
You and the Beifu soldiers will leave sooner or later.
您和北府兵也早晚都会离开
My brother once said
我哥哥曾说
that his best friend is an ambitious man,
他最好的朋友是个志向远大的人
whose lifelong wish
此生之愿
is to become the most powerful general in the world.
就是成为天底下最有权势的将军
You have indeed achieved it.
萧世子的确做到了
But Your Highness,
可世子
the most powerful person in the world
天下最有权势之人
is the emperor.
乃是帝王
For power,
世子为了这权势
will you really
当真会有一天
cross swords with my brother one day?
与我哥哥刀兵相向吗
According to what you said,
听你这话
it seems you are very certain
倒是你很确定
that your brother will stay in the palace.
你哥哥一定会留在宫中
We both know
你我皆知
that from the day my brother stepped into Jiankang Palace,
自我哥哥踏入剑慷宫那一日开始
it has become a dead end.
就已成死局
Even if the Empress Dowager has much dissatisfaction,
纵然太后有再多不满
she also knows
可她也知道
no one is a better candidate than my brother.
没有比我哥哥更合适的选择了
You brought Jiayu to see my brother today.
今日你让嘉鱼来见我哥哥
Although out of good intentions,
虽为好心
it's just a short-sighted fix.
却也不过是饮鸩止渴
Don't you want your brother
你难道不想让你哥哥
to be with the one he loves?
与心爱之人在一起吗
My brother has no way out.
哥哥他早已无退路
As for Jiayu,
而嘉鱼
she should be an eagle in the sky.
她该是天上的鹰
She doesn't want to be bound by these palace walls.
她不愿受这宫墙的束缚
As Jiayu's friend,
我作为嘉鱼的朋友
I also don't want her to enter the palace.
也不希望她入宫
You go back to the palace first.
你先回宫
As long as you don't show up tonight,
只要今晚你不出现
I promise your brother and Jiayu will be fine.
我保证你哥哥与嘉鱼无事
Mao.
阿茂
How much longer will you stay in the palace?
你还要在宫里待多久啊
Don't you like me being the Regent?
你不喜欢我做这个监国吗
I don't like it.
不喜欢
It feels very distant
感觉很遥远
and unfamiliar.
很陌生
They say
他们说
the Regent will become the Crown Prince next.
监国之后便是储君了
I haven't become one yet.
这不是还没当上吗
Besides, the Empress Dowager doesn't want me to either.
何况太后也不想让我做
Mao.
阿茂
Are you still willing to leave with me?
那你还愿意跟我一起走吗
Of course.
当然
I just want to be with the person I like the most.
我只想跟我最喜欢的人在一起
Excuse me.
借过 借过
Careful, Yaoyao.
小心 夭夭
It's the fake Xiao Sheng who bought the repeating crossbow.
这是那个买连环弩的假萧晟
It's that swindler!
是那个骗子
Yaoyao!
夭夭
Stop right there!
别跑
Tonight, the Empress Dowager will use the Young Master of Miraculous Craft
今夜太后要利用妙手公子
to cause a mutiny among the Beifu soldiers.
引起北府兵的哗变
Don't let Xie Jiayu get near the Monument of Loyalty.
千万不要让谢嘉鱼靠近忠义碑
Don't let her get involved.
别让她卷入其中
Yaoyao!
夭夭
Liu Yu'e.
柳玉娥
Madam Liu.
柳姑姑
Greetings, Your Highness.
参见世子
What are you doing at the Double Ninth Ceremony?
你来重阳大典做什么
The Empress Dowager has made a move tonight.
今夜太后有异动
Tell your people to leave quickly.
让你的人赶紧离开
Who's there?
谁
I trust you've fared well, Young Lord Xiao.
别来无恙 萧世子
Or I should call you
或者说
Crown Prince Wenxi.
文熹太子
Your Highness, with the Phoenix Heart Token,
郡主手持雀骨令
you haven't appeared for over 20 years.
二十余年不现身
Since you suddenly appear today,
今日突然出现
what are you after?
所图为何
I did have another purpose at first.
原本我的确有别的目的
But now I will use the Phoenix Heart Token
但如今我要用雀骨令
to set Yaoyao free.
还夭夭自由
What do you mean?
何意
I want you to pick a suitable time
我要你选个合适的时机
to divorce Yaoyao
与夭夭和离
and allow her to marry freely.
允她自由婚配
Although I don't like being threatened,
我虽不喜欢受人威胁
it's not difficult to do what you said.
但这并不难
I'm not finished.
我还没说完
Prince Qi is not suitable for Yaoyao.
岐王不适合夭夭
I want them to separate.
我要他们分开
If you can help me do this,
若太子能帮我做到这一点
I will be at your disposal, Your Highness.
云昭任凭殿下驱使
Halt!
站住
Yaoyao, don't go!
夭夭 别走
His Highness has ordered
世子有令
that you can't approach the Monument of Loyalty.
您不能靠近忠义碑
That is the fake Xiao Sheng who bought the repeating crossbow!
这是那个买连环弩的假萧晟
What?
什么
He's still alive?
他还活着
It's too late. Let's go!
来不及了 走
Yaoyao!
夭夭
Great!
好
Excuse me.
借过
Bright silver gold-painted spear,
亮银描金枪
weighing 24 jin,
重二十四斤
offered to General Zhang Zuwu.
祭张祖武将军
Armor-breaking blade,
破斩刀
weighing 48 jin,
重四十八斤
offered to General Li Wenzhong.
祭李文忠将军
To the heroic spirits above,
英灵在上
the Young Master of Miraculous Craft sends his regards.
妙手公子敬拜
It's done, Your Majesty.
成了 太后
Xie Jiayu has taken the bait.
谢嘉鱼入局了
Keeping Hong Qi alive is indeed useful.
留着洪七 果然有用
You really have great foresight.
您真是有先见之明啊
Look at how exquisitely this lantern is painted.
你看这花灯画得多精巧
I don't like it.
吾不喜欢
Look over there. Why is it on fire?
你看那儿 这怎么着火了
The Young Master of Miraculous Craft actually burned the offerings!
妙手公子竟然烧了祭品
Burned by the Young Master of Miraculous Craft.
妙手公子烧的
30,000 loyal souls return to their homeland.
三万忠魂 魂归故里
Seeing today's scene,
看到今日景象
I wonder what these 30,000 loyal souls
不知道这三万忠魂
would think.
如何作想
Beifu Army, listen to my orders!
北府军听令
-Yes!
在
Surround the altar
包围祭坛
and find the Young Master of Miraculous Craft.
找出妙手公子
The Beifu Army is killing people!
北府军杀人啦
-Murder! -Stop!
杀人啦 快住手
Stop!
住手
Hurry up and go!
快走
Beifu Army, listen up!
北府军听令
Do not harm the civilians!
不准伤及百姓
Stop!
住手
Your Highness, what took you so long?
世子 您怎么才来啊
I was delayed by something.
有事耽搁了
Has everything been arranged?
都安排好了吗
I didn't expect it to really be Fang Shiba and Lu Dayong.
没想到真是方十八 鲁大勇
Last time you whipped them,
上一次世子您鞭挞了他们
they must have held a grudge.
定是怀恨在心
They were bought off by the Empress Dowager
被太后买通
to incite the soldiers to mutiny.
才鼓动军兵作乱
Do it.
动手
Yes.
诺
Wait.
等等
Why is Xie Jiayu here too?
谢嘉鱼怎么也在这儿
Your Highness.
侧妃
Do not harm the civilians!
不可伤及百姓
The Monument of Loyalty is about to fall!
忠义碑快倒了
Everyone, run!
大家快跑
Run!
快跑啊
Yan Yue, quickly direct the civilians to run east.
偃月 你快指挥百姓往东边跑
Yao, run now!
大哥 快走
I don't know if this Soul-Chasing Bomb will work.
不知道这追魂弹管不管用
Are you alright, Yao?
没事吧 大哥
It's dangerous here.
这儿很危险
What are you doing here?
你来做什么
To save you.
为了救你啊
If my Soul-Chasing Bomb hadn't worked
要不是我的追魂弹管用
and shattered the Monument of Loyalty,
把这忠义碑炸碎了
and if it had fallen directly on you,
这要直接倒下来
you'd be dead now.
你人就没了
Yao, you're not hurt, are you?
大哥 你没受伤吧
I'm fine.
没事
Let Qing Long take you back first.
先让青龙送你回去吧
Yes.
诺
She is Xie Jiayu.
她就是谢嘉鱼
She is the Young Master of Miraculous Craft.
她就是妙手公子
She
就是她
blew up the Monument of Loyalty.
炸毁了忠义碑
Stop making false accusations.
你少含血喷人
I blew up the monument
我方才是为了救人
just now to save people.
才炸的忠义碑
Besides, it was about to fall anyway.
而且这碑本来就要倒了
Stop arguing.
你别狡辩了
The monument was perfectly fine. How could it fall?
忠义碑好端端的 怎么会倒
If not you,
如果不是你做的
then the wrath of 30,000 loyal souls.
那就是三万忠魂之怒
All because of you,
都是因为你
so many of our men died in the Northern Border.
我们在北境才死了这么多人
I will kill you
我要杀了你
to avenge our brothers!
替兄弟们报仇
Your Highness, if you protect her,
世子 若你保她
you are not fit to be the commander of the Beifu Army!
就不配做北府军的统帅
Fire!
走水了
Let's go.
走
His Highness is determined to protect the culprit.
世子铁了心要保这罪魁祸首啊
Are we just going to endure this?
我们就这样忍了吗
I'm in for what you suggested.
你说的事我参加
Your Highness.
殿下
Are you still going after her?
您还追吗
Tonight, Her Majesty and His Highness will surely have a showdown.
今夜太后和世子必有胜负
You can't get involved anymore.
您不能再卷进去了
But Yaoyao...
可是夭夭她
His Highness won't let anything happen to her.
世子不会让夭夭有事的
It's time to go back.
该回去了
[Hong Qi]
谢太后不杀之恩
I spared your life today.
吾今日饶你不死
From now on,
从此
you shall no longer exist in Jiankang City.
剑慷城就没你这个人了
Rest assured, Your Majesty.
请太后放心
Ready to move.
摆驾
-Who allowed you to go to the altar? -Who told you to hug me?
谁让你上祭台的 谁让你抱我的
-I did it to save you. -I did it to save people.
我是为了救你 我是为了救人
I think you're going to lose to me.
我觉得你要输给我了
Let's go.
走吧
When I say you're foolish,
说你傻
you really don't use your brain.
你就真不带脑子
We agreed that you would only be Qing Long tonight.
说好今夜你只当青龙
Qing Long?
青龙什么青龙
Would you arrange for Qing Long and Mao to meet and view lanterns?
你会安排青龙和阿茂见面看花灯
I shouldn't have arranged for you two to meet.
我就不该安排你们两个见面
What? Are you envious?
怎么 嫉妒啊
Are you jealous?
吃醋啊
Even if you are,
你就是嫉妒死
Mao only wants to see me,
阿茂也只想见我
not you.
不想见你
Don't think I haven't seen right through you.
你别以为我没看出来
The Empress Dowager making trouble today
今天太后生事
was all within your expectations.
全在你的意料之中
The Empress Dowager used me.
太后利用我
Father used me.
阿父利用我
Aren't you using me too?
你不是一样也在利用我吗
Make yourself clear.
你把话说清楚
When have I ever used you?
我什么时候利用过你
You had already arranged your men for tonight, right?
你今夜早就安排好了人手吧
The Empress Dowager intentionally tampered with the Monument of Loyalty
太后故意在忠义碑上做手脚
and used the Young Master of Miraculous Craft
利用妙手公子
to sow discord between you and the Beifu soldiers.
挑拨你和北府兵的关系
And you just played along.
你就顺水推舟
The paper weapons
纸糊的兵器
and those indignant Beifu soldiers—
还有那群义愤填膺的北府兵
weren't they all prepared by you?
不都是你准备的吗
You played along with her tricks,
你将计就计
making the Empress Dowager think she had won a total victory tonight.
让太后以为她今夜大获全胜
By making a risky move,
好兵行险招
you could completely grasp her weakness.
彻底抓住太后的把柄
Anyway, you just used me.
反正都是利用我
I went up to the altar
我上了祭台
and became a target of public criticism.
成为众矢之的
Didn't it help you make this play
不就帮你把这出戏
look more realistic?
演得越真越好吗
If you hadn't gotten involved, the title
若是你不掺和进来
of Young Master of Miraculous Craft would mean nothing.
妙手公子只是个名号
It wouldn't hurt you at all.
根本不会伤害到你
How could it not hurt me?
如何没有伤害到我
To you,
于你们而言
the Young Master of Miraculous Craft is just a title
妙手公子只是一个
that can be used to cause trouble.
可以作乱的名头
But for the past 16 years,
但妙手公子是这十六年来
it's the only thing that truly belongs to me.
唯一真正属于我自己的东西
Not Princess's daughter,
不是郡主的女儿
not Grand Tutor Xie's daughter.
不是谢太傅的女儿
It represents me, Xie Jiayu.
它所代表的是我谢嘉鱼自己
To you high and mighty people
它对于你们这些高高在上
who always talk about justice,
动辄天下大义的人来说
it may mean nothing.
或许什么意义都没有
You can use and abandon it at will.
随手便可利用 毁弃
But I created it
但它是我自己一点一滴
bit by bit.
创造出来的
And now,
而现在
it has been destroyed by you.
它已经被你们联手毁掉了
And you,
而你们
from the beginning to the end,
从始至终
didn't even ask me a word.
连问都没有问过我一句
Well, right,
也对
in your eyes,
在你萧无衣眼中
there are no innocent people in this world.
这世上没有无辜之人
For the sake of the world,
为了天下大事
you can even sacrifice yourself.
你连你自己都可以牺牲
Then what does
那我这一点小小的不甘心
my petty unwillingness amount to, after all?
又能算得了什么呢
This is the Shadow-Seeking Butterfly.
这是寻影蝶
I saw the fake Xiao Sheng
我今天是在人群中
in the crowd today,
看到了那个假萧晟
and that's why I went to the Shenwu Gate.
才去了神武门
I didn't mean to ruin your plan.
我不是故意要破坏你的计划的
I sprinkled scented powder on him.
我在他身上撒了香粉
If you send someone to chase him now,
你现在让人去追的话
it should still be in time.
应该还来得及
If you're lucky,
运气好的话
he might not be dead yet.
他或许还没死
You can use him against the Empress Dowager,
你要用他来对付太后
or my father.
或者我阿父
Either is fine.
都行
The name of the Young Master of Miraculous Craft
妙手公子之名
won't be destroyed.
不会被毁
Dare you come with me?
你敢不敢跟我走一趟
Where to?
去哪儿
The military camp.
军营
What's there to be afraid of?
这有什么不敢的
Let's play chess.
下棋
Master.
老师
Yaoyao said
夭夭说
you had a hand in those 30,000 fallen souls.
那三万人中也有您的手笔
Is it true?
这究竟是不是真的
Your Highness.
殿下
Let's play chess.
下棋
Whether Her Majesty wins or loses tonight,
今夜太后无论是胜还是败
to you, it's a battle between two rivals
对于你来说都是鹬蚌相争
that only benefits a third party.
渔翁得利
But I don't want to fight.
可我不想争啊
I just want Yaoyao to be safe.
我只想要夭夭平安
Really?
当真
Before, you were not in power,
从前殿下不在其位
so you didn't interfere in politics.
便不谋其政
You only needed to live well for yourself.
只需一粥一饭一人
Now you are only one step away from the supreme position.
如今离至尊之位只有一步之遥
Are you truly not interested
这天下棋局
in the game of this world at all?
当真一点都不感兴趣
Your Highness, do you know
殿下可知
that in the current situation,
当今之势
even the happiness of a simple meal,
即便是一粥一饭的幸福
without the protection of power,
若无权势庇佑
can be
亦可
overturned in an instant?
瞬间倾覆
But only
但唯有
the chess player
执棋者
can avoid harm.
才能够避免伤害
Your Highness,
殿下
this world is already in your hands,
这天下已在你手中
easily obtainable.
唾手可得
Do you really not want it?
你真的不想要吗
Your Majesty, there is news.
太后 有消息了
Speak.
说
Xiao Wuyi refused to hand over the Young Master of Miraculous Craft.
萧无衣不肯交出妙手公子
The soldiers of No. 36 Camp
三十六营的将士们
have already controlled him.
已经将他控制住
They want to use Xiao Wuyi and Xie Jiayu
他们想要用萧无衣和谢嘉鱼
to memorialize the fallen soldiers.
来祭奠阵亡的战士
Tonight, Prince Jing'an's Mansion and the Beifu Army
今夜靖安王府和北府军
will definitely fight to the death.
必将来个鱼死网破
Imperial Guard, hear my order.
禁军听令
Tonight, the Beifu Army's internal strife
今夜北府军内乱
will surely lead to a mutiny.
必起哗变
You must seize power at this opportunity.
尔等趁机夺势
Whoever seizes the Beifu Army's official seal
谁能夺取北府军大印
will take the greatest merit.
谁就立了头功
-Seize the seal, take the greatest merit!
夺大印 立头功
Her Majesty said
太后说
Xiao Wuyi has spent 10 years in military service,
萧无衣十年戎马
guarding the borders for Ye.
为大邺驻守边境
He should be properly seen off.
是该好好送一送
The impeachment must be written carefully.
弹劾要好好写
Do not forget his merits,
是功不要忘
and do not hide his faults.
是过不必藏
Tonight, it is the Beifu Army's own internal strife.
今夜是他北府军自生内乱
Do not let people
莫要让人
think that His Majesty and Her Majesty
以为是陛下和太后
has wronged him and ruined the world.
冤了他 误了天下
-We obey Her Majesty's decree.
谨遵太后懿旨
What is going on?
怎么回事
Could there be an ambush?
难不成有埋伏
This doesn't look like a mutiny.
这不像是哗变
Even if they don't revolt,
他们不乱
we must create chaos tonight.
今晚也要制造乱局
Eunuch He said,
贺公公说了
whoever gets the Beifu Army's official seal
谁能拿下北府军大印
takes the greatest merit!
谁就是头功
Oh no, an ambush!
不好 有埋伏
Quick, retreat!
快 撤
Everyone,
诸位
you are a step late.
你们来晚了一步
Arrest them all!
统统给我拿下
Subject to the Beifu military law,
北府军律
those who disturb military morale
扰乱军心者
shall be beheaded;
斩
those who incite mutiny
祸众哗变者
Fang Shiba,
方十八
5 days ago, you left the camp without permission
五日前你擅自出营
and secretly met with Commander Yue of the Imperial Guard.
密会了禁军岳统领
I didn't expect Yue Qingyang to use so little silver
想不到岳清扬用这么点银子
to buy the loyalty and trust of my Beifu soldiers.
就收买了我北府兵的军心和信任
What about you?
你们呢
Are you all like him?
也都和他一样吗
Disturbing military morale
扰乱军心
and rebelling,
谋逆叛乱
according to the law, you should be cut in half.
按律当腰斩
There is nothing to say.
没什么好说的
I'd say the silver is nothing.
要我说这些银子没什么
Commander Yue also promised me
岳统领还答应我
that if I succeeded,
如若事成
he would immediately transfer me to the Imperial Guard Camp
即刻将我调入禁军营
and transfer my household registration to Jiankang.
本贯户籍调入剑慷
It's better than being a Beifu soldier!
总好过做北府的兵
Shut up!
闭嘴
Take him away!
带下去
Execute him.
行刑
I've long been tired of eating sand and risking my life in Beifu!
我早就不想在北府吃沙子卖命了
I want to achieve great things!
我想建功立业
I want a better life for myself!
我想为自己的生活过好一点
Am I wrong?
我有错吗
What about you?
你呢
I joined Beifu not for glory,
我入北府不为功业
but for our country.
只为家国
I don't care about the Imperial Guard.
我不在乎什么禁军
I also accept military punishment.
我也认军法处置
But my father and brother both died in the Battle of Jiuzhang Plain.
只是我父兄皆死于九丈原一战
I will never let go
我绝对不会放过
of their murderers,
杀害他们的凶手
no matter who they are now!
不论现在是谁
Your Highness,
世子
are you really going to protect the culprit?
您真的要包庇罪魁吗
Culprit?
罪魁
Fine.
好
Then today, please open your eyes wide
那今日便请诸位擦亮眼睛
and see if the culprit in your eyes
看看你们眼中的罪魁
is truly the culprit.
到底是不是罪魁
I am Xie Jiayu.
我就是谢嘉鱼
These are the 18 weapons I specially forged
这些是我特意铸造的十八件兵器
to pay tribute to the 18 fallen Beifu generals.
来祭奠十八位阵亡的北府将军
I planned to offer them
本想在重阳之夜献至忠义碑前
But last night in front of the monument,
但昨夜忠义碑前
someone used the name of the Young Master of Miraculous Craft
有人借妙手公子之名
to sow discord in the Beifu Army.
挑拨北府军心
These are the fragments of the monument from last night.
这是昨夜忠义碑的碎石
This monument was carved from a plinth stone on the outside,
这石碑外用础石雕刻
but the inside was made of fragile sea rock.
但内里却用了易碎的海岩石
Once exposed to high temperatures,
一旦遇到高温
the inner core of the monument would burst.
石碑内胆就会发生爆裂
On the Double Ninth Festival,
昨日重阳
the monument was surrounded by lanterns sent by the Empress Dowager.
石碑四周皆是太后送来的花灯
There were over 100 of them.
足有上百只
Even if what happened last night had nothing to do with you,
就算昨夜之事与你无干
how do you explain the repeating crossbow?
那连环弩一事你又如何解释
Do you dare say you're not the Young Master of Miraculous Craft?
你敢说你不是妙手公子
Do you dare say the crossbow you designed
你敢说你设计的弓弩
didn't end up in the Beifu Army?
没有进入北府军中
Yes.
是
I am indeed the Young Master of Miraculous Craft.
我的确就是妙手公子
I also designed the repeating crossbow.
这连环弩也是我设计的
But I never knew
但我也从来不知道
this crossbow was designed for Beifu.
这弩是为北府而设计
Oranges thrive south of the Huai River,
橘生淮南则为橘
yet turn bitter north of it.
生于淮北则为枳
Everyone, please look.
诸位请看
Although there are many styles of the repeating crossbow,
此连弩虽有许多种样式
they're all meant for the young masters of noble families to hunt and play with,
但都是为了世家公子狩猎把玩
not designed for actual combat.
并非为实战而设计
If it were to be used in actual combat,
若要用于实战
the wood would need special treatment
此木材需要经过特殊处理
to be flexible enough.
才够柔韧
The person who came to me to buy the blueprint that day
当日来妙手找我买此图样之人
did not tell me its purpose.
并未告诉我用途
I really wonder
我也很想问
how such a repeating crossbow
这样一把连弩
could actually be sent to the Northern Border.
居然会被送去北境
If I had known this crossbow was designed for you,
如果我早知此弩是为你们而设计
I would have given you this one.
那我会给这把
Although it is not lightweight enough yet,
虽然还不够轻便
the range, power, and accuracy of this crossbow
但此弩的射程 力度 精准度
are what make it fit for the battlefield.
才配上战场
Try it.
试试看
This
这
is the true skill of the Young Master of Miraculous Craft.
才是我妙手公子的本事
As for the death of your father and brother,
你父兄之死
I am very sorry.
我很遗憾
But I can't give you the answer you want,
但你要的答案我也回答不了
because I also really want to ask
因为我也很想问
why such a crossbow,
这样一把
originally meant for young masters of noble families to play with,
本是世家公子把玩的弓弩
would be forged in large quantities,
为何会被大量铸造
smoothly passed through the court's strict inspections,
又顺利经过朝廷重重检查
and finally sent to the Beifu Army.
最后被送到北府军中
This is not something the Young Master of Miraculous Craft
这不是一个妙手公子
and one blueprint could achieve.
和一张图纸能够做到的
The Household Department makes the weapons.
兵器是少府在造
The problem lies with them.
问题出在少府
On his first day back in Jiankang,
世子回剑慷第一日
His Highness killed Household Department Adjutant Wei Qianli.
就杀了少府府丞魏千里
My Beifu soldiers fight for their lives on the battlefield,
我北府兵在战场上生死拼杀
yet the court is full of useless officials.
朝廷却多尸位素餐之人
Is it enough to just kill a Household Department Adjutant?
杀了一个少府府丞就够了吗
For the innocent souls who died in vain
为了这些枉死的冤魂
and for the future safety of the Northern Border,
也为了北境日后的安危
it's time to change all this.
是到了改变这一切的时候了
Titles based on military merit.
军功定爵
Dismissal of hereditary nobles.
裁汰世卿
All will start from Beifu.
自北府始
Please wait for today's court assembly!
请诸位静待今日朝会
-We will obey your orders, Your Highness!
我等谨遵世子军令
The death penalty can be spared,
死罪可免
but punishment can't be avoided.
活罪难逃
Take them away.
带走
Give them the military flogging!
领军棍
Brother,
哥哥
who do you think will win today,
你说今日
the Empress Dowager
太后与萧世子
or Young Lord Xiao?
谁赢谁输啊
I don't know.
我不知道
If the Empress Dowager wins,
若是太后赢了
will we be able to leave here?
我们是可以离开这儿
Or will we die?
还是会死
Why is it always us
为什么每一次
who can't control our own fate
无法掌控自己命运
and are at the mercy of others
任人宰割之人
every single time?
都是我们呢
Your Majesty,
禀太后
I have a matter to report.
臣有事要奏
Her Majesty is unwell today.
今日太后身体不适
Please report tomorrow.
明日再奏
I want to impeach Xiao Wuyi, Heir of Prince Jing'an.
臣要弹劾靖安王世子萧无衣
-I also want to impeach Xiao Wuyi.
臣也要弹劾萧无衣
My ministers, I've been unwell these past few days.
众卿家 这几日吾身子不适
If there is no solid proof,
若无实证
do not cause trouble in the court.
就不要来朝堂添乱了
Your Majesty,
太后
all the ministers want to impeach Young Lord Xiao.
众臣皆想弹劾萧世子
We might as well listen.
不如听下去
If he is truly guilty,
若真有罪
Young Lord Xiao should be punished by the law of the state right here.
萧世子在此当以国法论处
Since you've written them,
写都写了
what is there that can't be said?
有什么不能说的
Which of you will go first?
你们几个谁先来啊
You go first.
你来吧
I believe Young Lord Xiao abused his military power,
臣以为萧世子滥用军权
mobilized troops without authorization,
私调军队
and deceived his superiors and subordinates,
欺上瞒下
leading to a mutiny in the Beifu Army.
致北府兵变
I now petition you, Your Majesty,
今奏请陛下 太后
to strip Xiao Wuyi of his Beifu Army military seal,
褫夺萧无衣北府军帅印
strip him of his rank, imprison him,
夺职下狱
and punish him according to his crimes.
论罪处罚
I impeach Xiao Wuyi on 29 charges.
臣弹劾萧无衣罪状有二十九
First,
其一
he disrupted the Double Ninth Festival Ceremony,
祸乱重阳祭典
caused a mutiny in the army,
引起军中哗变
and disturbed the people.
扰乱民心
Second, as the military commander, Xiao Wuyi
其二 萧无衣身为军中统帅
seized his subordinate's widow
霸占下属遗孀
and is highly debauched.
荒淫无度
Third, Xiao Wuyi—
其三 萧无衣
Are there really that many charges?
当真有这么多条啊
It's a long list of crimes,
可真是罪行累累
too numerous to record.
罄竹难书啊
Let me speak for you.
我替你说吧
Your Majesty, since I have committed so many crimes,
太后 既然臣犯下这么多罪行
I wonder how you
不知陛下与太后
will convict me.
将要如何给臣定罪啊
Nonsense.
胡说八道
Young Lord Xiao is a pillar of our Ye.
萧世子乃我大邺柱石
How can I allow you to slander him?
岂容尔等诬蔑
Untie him at once.
还不赶紧松绑
Your Majesty, this...
太后 这
Hurry and untie him!
还不快去松绑
Vice Minister Qi,
齐侍郎
how did you know about the mutiny in my Beifu Army?
你怎知我北府军哗变的
Who told you?
谁告诉你的
If you are innocent, why were you tied up?
你没罪 那你怎么被绑
Last night, a band of bandits broke into my camp.
昨夜一伙盗匪闯入我军营
They have been captured by the Beifu Army.
已被北府军齐心拿下
Your Majesty, the Beifu Army Camp is safe and sound,
太后 北府军营安然无恙
and can still protect you and His Majesty.
依然可以保卫您与陛下
You can rest assured now.
太后这下可放心了
Young Lord Xiao, with you here,
有萧世子在
I am at ease.
吾自然安心
However,
不过
these bandits claimed to be from the Imperial Guard,
这伙盗匪却自称是禁军出身
saying they were ordered by someone noble in the palace
说是奉宫中贵人之命
to instigate a mutiny in the Beifu Army.
前来挑唆北府哗变
By order of the palace?
奉宫中之命
But I thought...
但臣以为
this was absolutely impossible.
此事绝无可能
So I killed them all.
所以臣把他们都杀了
I bound myself and came to the court today
臣今日自缚上殿
just to let you see, Your Majesty,
正是想让太后看看
how many courtiers in the palace
宫中到底有多少朝臣
are hoping to make an issue of this.
盼着以此事做文章
Now it's great.
这下好了
All the treacherous ministers have jumped out.
奸臣们全都跳出来了
You did well and right to kill them, Young Lord Xiao.
萧世子杀得好 杀得对
The Imperial Guard guards the imperial city
禁军戍守皇城
and forms a bond with the Beifu Army,
与北府军情同手足
together defending Ye.
共同守卫大邺
Your Majesty,
太后
I also have a memorial to present today.
臣今日也有本奏
Go ahead.
奏
All the causes today
今日一切之故
lie in the military system.
皆在军制
The bows and crossbows played by young masters of noble families
世家公子玩乐的弓弩
were sent to the army without inspection,
未经检验就被送入军中
causing the wrongful deaths of the troops in Jiuzhang Plain.
致九丈原将士枉死
Those from poor families who want to join the Imperial Guard
出身寒门者想要投身禁军
must first enter noble families to pass the assessment.
必须先入世家门下才能通过考核
Grain and military provisions run short every year,
粮草军需年年短缺
and the pay is in arrears every year.
人头饷年年拖欠
Even the Imperial Guard, which symbolizes the royal family's dignity,
就连象征着皇家颜面的禁军
can be easily disguised by bandits.
也能被盗匪轻易假扮
What does all this show?
这一切都说明了什么
It shows that the military system of our dynasty has been deeply flawed
说明我朝军制沉疴
and rotten for a long time.
痼疾久矣
To cut weeds, you must dig up the roots.
斩草须除根
To control water, you must treat the source.
治水当治源
I've drafted the preliminary proposal on the "Discourse on Beifu Reform"
臣初拟《北府改制论》条呈
and presented it to you, Your Majesty.
呈于陛下 太后
Abolish hereditary soldiers, implement recruitment,
废世兵 行募选
formalize the garrison system, set up ever-normal granaries,
定府制 立平仓
establish studs, value humble talents,
设马场 重寒门
reduce private troops, and unify commands.
削私兵 统号令
Reform Beifu
改制北府
to clarify rewards and punishments.
明察赏罚
Please approve it, Your Majesty.
请陛下 太后允准
Who dares to stop Her Majesty's carriage?
何人敢拦太后鸾驾
Xiao Wuyi?
萧无衣
Didn't you—
你不是被
Your Majesty, are you waiting for a mutiny in the Beifu Army?
太后是在等北府军中哗变吗
I'm afraid you won't see it.
您怕是等不到了
Your Majesty,
太后
this is Commander Yue's head!
这是岳统帅的人头
Xiao Wuyi!
萧无衣
Last night, those from the Imperial Guard who disrupted my Beifu Army Camp
昨夜这些祸乱我北府军营的禁军
were all punished according to military regulations by me.
臣皆以军规处置
Now the Beifu Army Camp is in perfect order.
如今的北府军营秩序井然
Her Highness's Shadow-Seeking Butterfly is really useful,
侧妃的寻影蝶真好用
much more accurate than the ordinary scented powder
比咱们军中斥候用的普通香粉
used by the scouts in our army.
精准多了
Hong Qi,
洪七
why aren't you dead yet?
你怎么还没死
If you don't want Eunuch Hong to go to the court
太后若不想让洪公公走上朝堂
and make your actions public...
将太后所为公之于众
What do you want?
你想要什么
I ask you to preside over
臣请太后主持
the Beifu reform.
北府改制
Your loyalty
世子忠心
can be seen by heaven and earth.
天地可鉴
The reform proposal requested by you
世子所请改制疏
is approved for joint discussion by the Department of State Affairs.
准尚书台合议
-This...
这 这 这
Thank you, Your Majesty.
谢太后
I have another matter to report.
臣还有一事奏报
Since the great defeat at Jiuzhang Plain,
自九丈原大败
the morale of the Northern Qin army has been greatly frustrated.
北秦军心大挫
The Emperor of Northern Qin wants to send a delegation for peace talks.
北秦皇帝欲遣使团议和
This all relies on His Majesty's prestige and your benevolence.
这都是仰仗陛下威名与太后仁德
Congratulations,
臣恭喜太后
Your Majesty.
贺喜太后
Young Lord Xiao, you're too modest.
萧世子过谦了
How would I know about the war in the Northern Border?
北境战事吾哪里懂
Today's peace
今日的和平
all relies on you
都要仰仗你
and the Beifu troops fighting bloody battles.
和北府将士浴血奋战啊
As for these peace talks,
这和谈之事
I'll leave it to you...
便交给萧世子
and Prince Qi to negotiate together.
和岐王一起去商谈吧
You should emulate the diplomatic wisdom of Lin Xiangru and Lian Po
当效蔺廉折冲之智
to show the conciliatory virtue of our Ye.
彰我大邺怀柔之德
A little bit to the right.
往右边一点点
Yes.
对
Right here.
就这儿
Young Master of Miraculous Craft,
妙手公子
have you finally made up your mind
终于下定决心
to spend money to rent this shop?
肯花银子租下这铺位了
Yes.
是啊
I used to be reluctant to spend money
从前不舍得花银子
and always borrowed other people's shops.
总是借别人的铺子
From now on,
今日开始
my own shop is officially open.
我自己的铺子正式开张
-Great!
好 好
From now on, everyone will know
以后所有人都知道
that I, Xie Jiayu, am the Young Master of Miraculous Craft.
我谢嘉鱼就是妙手公子
Young Lord Xiao, we have to thank you for your help
这还要多谢萧世子帮忙
in officially registering the shop with the government.
将铺子在官府正式记档
With Beifu as a guarantor,
有了北府作保
My Lady, you can openly
日后女郎就可以光明正大地
research and manufacture weapons in the future.
研究武器营造了
He doesn't lose out either.
他也不亏
I also promised to help him modify the armaments.
我还答应帮他改造军械呢
Yue,
月姐姐
may I borrow your sword?
可否借你的剑一用
From now on, there is only Miraculous Craft in the world.
以后天下只有妙手
I, Xie Jiayu,
我谢嘉鱼
even as a woman in this world,
就算是女子之身立世
can stand upright and honorable.
也一样堂堂正正
-Great!
好 好 好
Great!
好
I think it's great.
我觉得很好
I think so too.
我也觉得
Let's go. I'll buy you drinks today.
走吧 今日我请你们喝酒
-Let's go. -Let's go in.
走吧 我们进去
You are included, Xiao Wuyi.
算你一个啊 萧无衣
Thank you for allowing me to clear the name of Miraculous Craft.
多谢你给我机会为妙手正名
Let's go.
走吧
I haven't seen the Young Lady this happy in a long time.
好久都没见女郎这么开心了
I haven't seen His Highness this relaxed in a long time either.
我也很久没见世子如此放松了
This is what happens when you drink.
让你喝
You are so bad at drinking.
这么不能喝酒
I shouldn't have let you touch a drop.
我就该一滴酒都不让你碰
Nonsense.
胡说
I have a great tolerance.
我酒量可好了
I can drink two Maos
我能喝倒
under the table.
两个阿茂
What's the number?
几
Two.
两个
Isn't it two?
不是两个阿茂吗
If you really can't walk,
你要实在走不了
why don't you find a carriage?
要不就找个马车吧
You are a lady of a noble family after all.
你好歹也是个世家淑女
I am not a lady of a noble family.
我本来我就不是什么世家淑女
I was taken in by my father and mother.
我是我阿父阿母捡回来的
What did you just say?
你刚说什么
Nothing.
没什么
Xiao Wuyi,
萧无衣
considering that today,
我看在今天呢
you helped me save my title as Miraculous Craft,
你帮我保住这妙手的份上
I will give you a piece of advice.
我给你一句忠告
Come here.
过来
Come closer, come on.
过过过
When it comes to romantic relationships,
这感情的事啊
it can't be forced.
它勉强不来的
You
你呀
need to be more open-minded.
凡事都得看开一点
Look,
那你看
Ruisheng and Yuanji
那人家蕊生阿姊和元姬阿姊
both have someone they like.
都有心上人了
You didn't know that, did you?
这你就不知道吧
Forget it.
算了
It's good that you don't know.
你不知道吧 也有不知道的好
I think it's good.
我觉得挺好
This prayer tablet
这个福牌啊
is very effective.
很灵的
It can bless all lovers in the world
它能保佑这天底下的有情人
will never part.
都不分离
I saw the other day
我那天看
that Ruisheng and Yuanji
蕊生阿姊和元姬阿姊
both inscribed words on their tablets.
她们都写了
Mao and I did it too.
我和阿茂也写了一个
I'll give it to you today.
我今天把它给你
Let the heavens bless you.
你多让老天爷保佑保佑你吧
Keep it.
拿好
Could it be that you...
你这该不会是
Yes.
对啊
I saw that the Double Ninth Tree
我看那个重阳树上
is full of these prayer tablets.
挂的都是这祈福牌
Very effective.
很灵的
Try it.
试试啊
Double Ninth,
重阳 重阳
for endless longing for those gone before.
思念故人
The name inscribed on this prayer tablet
写在这祈福牌上的名字
foretells either parting in life or separation by death.
不是生离就是死别
So unlucky.
这么不吉利
Never mind, I'd better not tell her.
罢了 还是别告诉她了
I'm telling you,
我跟你说啊
if there is no war in the future,
这以后天下不打仗
Mao and I
我和阿茂我们两个人呢
will travel the world.
就去游历天下
That's great.
真好
Where do you want to go?
那你们想去哪儿啊
We'll first go to...
我们先去
Yazhou.
崖州
♪ Tugs the threads woven by fate ♪
听说那边的海可漂亮了
Then we will go to the northwest.
然后再去西北
You have to host us then.
到时候你可得招待我们啊
Sure.
好
Then I want the strongest wine.
那我要最烈的酒
I'm afraid you won't dare to drink it.
就怕你不敢喝
I dare.
敢
♪ Fear no partings or wax and wane ♪
我可敢喝酒
Let's go.
走
Your Highness, you want me to break up Yizhi and your daughter.
郡主想让我拆散易之和令爱
But have you ever thought about this?
但郡主可曾想过
If it weren't for Prince Qi,
若不是有岐王
I wouldn't agree so easily
我不会这么轻易答应
to give Xie Jiayu her freedom.
还谢嘉鱼自由
Even with the Phoenix Heart Token in your hand,
即便是郡主手持雀骨令
you wouldn't have that kind of influence.
也没有这样的面子
For those who suffered hardships in their youth,
少时颠簸不幸之人
survival is the first priority.
生存乃第一要务
Apprenticeships, reputation, and marriage
拜师 声名 婚姻
are all ways to survive in this world.
皆立世生存之道
Prince Qi is not a good match for Jiayu.
岐王并非嘉鱼良配
Let's make a bet.
你我赌一局
Prince Qi will not leave Jiankang with Yaoyao.
岐王不会再和夭夭离开剑慷
This is what your mother left you.
这是你母后留给你的
It is said that this Phoenix Heart Token
据说这雀骨令中
contains wealth that could overturn the world.
蕴藏着能够颠覆天下的财富
The Phoenix Heart Token or Xie Jiayu?
雀骨令还是谢嘉鱼
The choice is easy.
这个选择很容易
I have never believed that a few tokens
我从来就不相信几枚令牌
could overturn the world.
就能令天下翻覆
If you're willing to pledge allegiance to me with the token,
郡主若愿持令归附
I will not object.
我不反对
If you wish to remain silent as you have for the past 10 years,
若愿继续像这十几年般沉默
that is also fine.
亦可
But I will never be coerced.
但无衣决不受人胁迫
There is no need
交易
for a deal.
就不必了
I can help you.
我可以帮你
I can help you find the last token holder.
去找最后一个持令之人
Since you want to fight the noble families
太子要与世家斗
and reform Beifu,
要推行北府改制
you need all the help you can get.
都需助力
Since my sister-in-law said
既然皇嫂说过
that this Phoenix Heart Token hides the wealth of the world,
这雀骨令中藏尽天下财富
it will certainly help you.
那就一定可以帮到你
I only want my daughter to be happy.
我只要我女儿幸福
I can promise you,
我可以答应你
but no one can force Xie Jiayu
但任何人都无法逼迫谢嘉鱼
to go against her own will,
违背她的本心
including her father
包括她的父亲
and Prince Qi.
也包括岐王
Xie Jiayu has the freedom to choose.
谢嘉鱼拥有选择的自由
Including you,
也包括你
Your Highness.
太子殿下
Naturally.
自然
Including me.
也包括我
I, Yunzhao,
臣云昭
am willing to serve you, Your Highness,
愿为殿下驱使
and find the Phoenix Heart Token.
寻找雀骨令